<?xml version="1.0"?>
<command-def xmlns="http://www.unix4j.org/command-def"
			 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
			 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.unix4j.org/command-def command-def.xsd">

	<command name="sed" class="org.unix4j.unix.Sed" package="org.unix4j.unix.sed"/>
	<name>sed - stream editor for filtering and transforming text</name>
	<synopsis>
		sed script
		
		sed s/orig/rep/flags, flags=gp#
		sed =
		sed a \
		sed i \
		sed c \
		sed /pat/ d
		sed /pat/ p
		sed addr q
		sed y/src/dst/
		options: -n --quiet --silent	
	</synopsis>
	<description ref="sed.html"/>
	<notes>
	</notes>
	<methods>
		<method args="args" usesStandardInput="false">
			Executes the sed script specified by the given arguments and writes
			the result to the standard output. 
			
			Options can be specified by acronym (with a leading dash "-") or by 
			long name (with two leading dashes "--"). Operands other than the 
			default "--script" operand have to be prefixed with the operand name. 
		</method>
		<method args="script" usesStandardInput="false">
			Executes the given sed script, such as "s/original/replacement/g".
		</method>
		<method args="regexp,replacement" usesStandardInput="false">
			Substitutes the replacement string for instances of the regexp in 
			the matched line.
			
			An ampersand ('&amp;') appearing in the replacement is be replaced 
			by the line matching the regexp. The characters "\n", where n is a 
			digit, are replaced by the text matched by the corresponding 
			backreference expression.  The special meaning of '&amp;' and "\n" 
			in this context can be suppressed by preceding it by a backslash. 

			A line can be split by substituting a newline ('\n') into it. 
			
			A substitution is considered to have been performed even if the 
			replacement string is identical to the string that it replaces. 
		</method>
		<method args="regexp,replacement,occurrence" usesStandardInput="false">
			Substitutes the replacement string for instances of the regexp in 
			the matched line. Only the given occurrences of the regexp found 
			within the matched string are substituted. 
			
			An ampersand ('&amp;') appearing in the replacement is be replaced 
			by the line matching the regexp. The characters "\n", where n is a 
			digit, are replaced by the text matched by the corresponding 
			backreference expression.  The special meaning of '&amp;' and "\n" 
			in this context can be suppressed by preceding it by a backslash. 

			A line can be split by substituting a newline ('\n') into it. 
			
			A substitution is considered to have been performed even if the 
			replacement string is identical to the string that it replaces. 
		</method>
		<method args="options,regexp" usesStandardInput="false">
			Executes the sed command specified by the given options or executes
			the print command p if no command option has been declared.
		</method>
		<method args="options,string1,string2" usesStandardInput="false">
			Executes the sed command specified by the given options or executes
			the substitute command s if no command option has been declared.
		</method>
		<method args="options,string1,string2,occurrence" usesStandardInput="false">
			Executes the sed command specified by the given options or executes
			the substitute command s if no command option has been declared.
			
			The string1 operand usually contains the regular expression matched 
			against a line for all commands except for command y where string1 
			contains the source characters for the translation.
			
			The string2 operand contains the replacement string for the 
			substitute command s. It contains the appended, inserted or changed 
			text for the commands a, i and c, respectively, and the destination 
			characters for the translate command y. All other commands ignore
			the string2 operand.
		</method>
	</methods>
	<options>
		<option acronym="n" name="quiet">
			Suppress the default output (in which each line, after it is 
			examined for editing, is written to standard output). Only lines 
			explicitly selected for output are written.		
		</option>
		<option acronym="g" name="global">
			Globally substitute for all non-overlapping instances of the regexp 
			rather than just the first one. 
			
			(This option is ignored if the occurrence operand is specified).
		</option>
		<option acronym="p" name="print">
			Write the matched line to standard output.
		</option>
		<option acronym="l" name="lineNumber">
			Writes the current line number on a separate line to the standard 
			output.
		</option>
		<option acronym="I" name="ignoreCase">
			Use case insensitive pattern matching.
		</option>
		<option acronym="s" name="substitute" exclusiveGroup="command">
			Substitutes the replacement string for instances of the regexp in 
			the matched line.
			
			An ampersand ('&amp;') appearing in the replacement is be replaced 
			by the line matching the regexp. The characters "\n", where n is a 
			digit, are replaced by the text matched by the corresponding 
			backreference expression.  The special meaning of '&amp;' and "\n" 
			in this context can be suppressed by preceding it by a backslash. 

			A line can be split by substituting a newline ('\n') into it. 
			
			A substitution is considered to have been performed even if the 
			replacement string is identical to the string that it replaces. 
		</option>
		<option acronym="a" name="append" exclusiveGroup="command">
			Append string2 as a separate line after the matched line.
		</option>
		<option acronym="i" name="insert" exclusiveGroup="command">
			Insert string2 as a separate line before the matched line.
		</option>
		<option acronym="c" name="change" exclusiveGroup="command">
			Write string2 as a separate line instead of the matched line.
		</option>
		<option acronym="d" name="delete" exclusiveGroup="command">
			Delete the matched line.
		</option>
		<option acronym="y" name="translate" exclusiveGroup="command">
			Replace all occurrences of characters in string1 with the 
			corresponding characters in string2. If the number of characters in 
			the two strings are not equal, or if any of the characters in 
			string1 appear more than once, the results are undefined.
		</option>
	</options>
	<operands default="script">
		<operand name="script" type="String">
			Sed script as one string, such as "s/original/replacement/g".
		</operand>
		<operand name="regexp" type="String">
			Regular expression matched against a line.
		</operand>
		<operand name="string1" type="String">
			Regular expression matched against a line for all commands except 
			for command y where string1 contains the source characters for the 
			translation.
		</operand>
		<operand name="replacement" type="String">
			Replacement string for substitute command. An ampersand ('&amp;') 
			appearing in the replacement string is replaced by the string 
			matching the regular expression. The characters "\n", where n is a 
			digit, are replaced by the text matched by the corresponding 
			backreference expression. The special meaning of '&amp;' and "\n" in 
			this context can be suppressed by preceding it by a backslash.  
		</operand>
		<operand name="string2" type="String">
			Replacement string for substitute command s; appended, inserted or
			changed text for a, i and c command; destination characters for
			translate command y; ignored by all other commands.
			
			If string2 is a replacement string for the substitute command: an 
			ampersand ('&amp;') appearing in the replacement string is replaced 
			by the string matching the regular expression; the characters "\n", 
			where n is a digit, are replaced by the text matched by the 
			corresponding backreference expression. The special meaning of 
			'&amp;' and "\n" in this context can be suppressed by preceding it 
			by a backslash.

			(This operand only applies to the commands s, a, i, c and y and is 
			ignored by all other commands).
		</operand>
		<operand name="occurrence" type="int...">
			Substitute for the given occurrences only of the regexp found within 
			the matched string; the occurrence indices are one-based. If empty 
			or omitted, all occurrences are substituted.
			
			(This operand only applies to the substitute command and is ignored
			by all other commands).
		</operand>
		<operand name="args" type="String...">
			String arguments defining the options and operands for the command. 
			Options can be specified by acronym (with a leading dash "-") or by 
			long name (with two leading dashes "--"). Operands other than the
			default "--script" operand have to be prefixed with the operand name
			(e.g. "--occurrence" for subsequent occurrence indices).
		</operand>
		<operand name="options" type="SedOptions">
			Sed options and commands
		</operand>
	</operands>
</command-def>